Guide to the Fishing Manuscripts Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Fishing manuscripts collection
1610-1966
GEN MSS 834
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.21
(6 boxes)
Collection consists of manuscripts, typescripts, photographs, and other documents relating to fishing, flies for fishing, and fishing trips taken in England and North America. Most of the items were formerly in the collection of David Wagstaff.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Isabelle Tilford Wagstaff, 1951-1953. Purchased from Wormser on the David Wagstaff Memorial Fund, 1952. Gift of Vernon S. Hidy, 1968, 1975. Gift of Lindley Eberstadt, 1969. Purchased from Henry Bristow on the Jonathan O. Bulkley Fund, 1994. Purchased from Rodolphe Chamonal on the David Wagstaff Fund, 2003. For further information see Collections Contents list.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Fishing Manuscripts Collection consists of manuscripts, typescripts, photographs, and other documents relating to fishing, flies for fishing, and fishing trips taken. Most of the items were formerly in the collection of David Wagstaff (1882-1951).
David Wagstaff (1882-1951)
David Wagstaff, broker, sportsman and collector of sporting books, paintings and prints, served as the Curator of Sporting Books in the Yale University Library from 1943 to 1951.
Arrangement
Arranged by previously assigned consecutive numbers.
Fishing; Fly fishing; Flies, Artificial; Adirondack Mountains (N.Y.); Restigouche River (N.B. and Québec); Drawings (visual works); Watercolors (paintings); Bainbridge, Geo. C. (George Cole), 1788-1839; Barker, Thomas, active 1651; Brady, Cyrus Townsend, 1861-1920; Fitzgibbon, Edward, 1803-1857; Gosden, Thomas, 1780-1843; Harrison, George, 1872-1956; Holberton, Wakeman; Jackson, John, of Tanfield Mill; Lathy, Thomas Pike, 1771-1841; Leisenring, James E.; Lum, Frederick Harvey; Sharswood, George, 1810-1883; Slaney, Moreton Aglionby, 1765-1817; Thorold, John Hayford, Sir, 1773-1831; Wagstaff, David, 1882-1951; Willis Bund, J. W. (John William), 1843-1928; Bainbridge, George Cole -- Bookplate; Denison, Alfred -- Bookplate; Gosden, Thomas, 1780-1843 -- Bookplate; Guise, William V. -- Bookplate; Heckscher, John Gerard -- Bookplate; Sage, Dean, 1841-1902 -- Bookplate; Wagstaff, David, 1882-1951 -- Bookplate
- Fishing Manuscripts, 1610-1966; 2.21; (6 boxes)
  - 1. Directions for making Artificial Flies, by Samuel Jemmat of Devonshire, Esq., given to me by his son, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Isabelle Tilford Wagstaff, 1951.
    General note
    Manuscript in unidentified hand, bound in three-quarters green leather with marbled boards; 8 leaves, 16.5 cm.
    With bookplate of Dean Sage.
  - 2. Flies for the Rivers Exe, Devon, & Barle, Somerset, by I. N. B., circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Manuscript in unidentified hand, bound in vellum envelope cover; 25 leaves, 15 cm..
    With signature of H. M. Waugh, HMS Kent, and engraved book ticket of John Brown, stationer of London.
  - 3. Of Artificial Flies and the Seasons proper for using them, by George Cole Bainbridge., circa 1812 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Autograph manuscript; bound in red roan, with case; 124 pages, 18 cm.
    At end are four leaves containing watercolor sketches of insects and a pencil sketch of a river scene with castle.
    "The original manuscript material for The Fly-Fisher's Guide " (Dean Sage, Catalogue of Books on Angling ).
    Laid in are several autograph memoranda and other memoranda (dating from 1778-1841) in several unidentified hands. Author's autograph inscription dated 1812 inside front cover.
    With bookplate of Dean Sage. With a note in David Wagstaff's hand: "Tayleure sale, 1828, 281"; from the Grego collection
  - 4. Angling commonplace books (3 volumes), circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    Manuscript in an unidentified hand, with some clippings pasted in; 18-20.5 cm.
  - 5. General Observations to be Understood by all such who desire to attain to the Compleat and perfect art of Angling, circa 1763 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Manuscript written in an unidentified hand, bound in black morocco with cover title: Old M.S.S. on angling; dated 1763 on flyleaf, in an unidentified hand; 48 pages, 24.5 cm.
    With two bookplates of John Gerard Heckscher, and autograph presentation inscription from F. Wright to F. M. Walhan, dated June 4, 1892
  - 6. Journal of Miss Peggy Harrison on the Ristigouche, June 1929, circa 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Typescript, 1 of 2 copies, bound in tan buckram; 45 leaves; 28 cm.
    Accompanied by an autograph letter signed from George Harrison (1872-1956) of St. Davids, Pennsylvania, to David Wagstaff, concerning the manuscript about his daughter's trip, dated July 9, 1930.
  - 7. The Baby Goes A-Fishing, by Cyrus Townsend Brady, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Autograph manuscript, bound in three-quarter red morocco, with marbled boards; 10 pages, 26 cm.
    With bookplate of David Wagstaff
  - 8. The Nipigon River: account of a fishing trip in the summer of 1873
    Manuscript in unidentified hand, likely that of Philadelphia lawyer George Sharswood, with nine photographs bound in as plates; bound in three-quarters green morocco; 64 pages, 24 cm.
    With bookplate of George Sharswood
  - 9. The Angler: bibliographical notes, mainly concerning works on angling and archery, written in an unidentified hand., undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Manuscript, bound in three-quarters green calf, with marbled boards and spine title: The Angler. M.S.S. Walton and Cotton, Etc.; 50 leaves, 23.5 cm
    With bookplate of Dean Sage
  - 10. Of Fishing, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Manuscript in an eighteenth century hand, prefaced by a prayer in another hand; bound by Rivière; 180 pages, 19 cm.
  - 11. The Angler: a poem in ten cantos, by Thomas Pike Lathy, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Autograph manuscript of the volume published by W. Wright in 1819; 115 leaves, 24 cm.
    With bookplates of Alfred Denison, Thomas Gosden, and David Wagstaff
  - 12. Jottings Down, by one of our trouting party, 1858 Jun (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Manuscript by an unidentified author from New York, about his fishing trip to the Adirondacks with three friends from Boston, dated June 1858; 18 pages, 32.5 cm.
  - 13. Papers relating to David Wagstaff's membership in the Ristigouche Salmon Club
    Separated Materials
    Documents were removed from this collection and added to David Wagstaff Papers (GEN MSS 415).
  - 14. Noted Angling Resorts, by Wakeman Holberton, 1890
    Pen and ink drawings (31) with title page, index, and a watercolor frontispiece; contains images of noted fishing spots in New York, Pennsylvania, Maine, and Quebec; bound in citron morocco with gilt borders and dentelles; 31 pages, 28 cm.
    Gift of Isabelle Tilford Wagstaff, 1952.
  - 15. The Art of angling, circa 1610 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Manuscript in an unidentified hand, bound in light brown calf; 76 pages, 16.5 cm.
    Bound in at front is a half leaf with the following headline: "A Craft to take pykes &c: [From an old ms. on vellum, written probably about 1550, in my [Thomas Gosden?] own possession]."
    On leaf preceding first page of manuscript, in another seventeenth century hand, "Natales muorum": 15 lines of genealogical notes.
    With bookplates of William V. Guise and David Wagstaff
  - 16. A Poetical Epistle from M.A.S. to Andrew Corbet of Acton Reyland Esq. on Fishing and Angling, by Moreton Aglionby Slaney, circa 1810 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Manuscript with one pen and pencil sketch, bound in three-quarters green calf, with marbled boards; 49 pages, 24 cm.
    Slaney (1765-1817) was the brother-in-law of Sir Andrew Corbet.
    With bookplate of David Wagstaff.
  - 17. A Treatise of the Art of Taking Pike, Pearch, Chub &c, with the Trimmer to which is added a description of the Necessary Tackle together with directions for its use &c &c., by Thomas Gosden [?], 1820 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Manuscript with a few pencil sketches, bound in three-quarters green morocco, with marbled boards; 27 leaves, 26 cm.
    With bookplates of Alfred Denison and David Wagstaff.
  - 18. A Chronological List of English Books on Angling, 1496-1917, circa 1917 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Purchased from Wormser on the David Wagstaff Memorial Fund, 1952
    Manuscript in an unidentified hand, bound in brown half morocco; 331 pages, 21 cm.
    Autograph of C. O. P. Gibson, Bywell Castle, Stocksfield, Northumberland (October 1923) and bookplate of John Wayland Leslie, Combe Court
  - 19. Salmon Problems, by John William Willis Bund, 1885 Aug (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Gift of Isabelle Tilford Wagstaff, 1953.
    Typescript, bound in maroon morocco; 325 pages, 24 cm.
    Willis Bund (1843-1928) was the chairman of the Severn Fishing Board.
  - 20. Miscellaneous notes relating to Thomas Barker and his Art of Angling, by James Williamson., undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Manuscripts tipped into notebook bound in three-quarter green morocco with marbled boards, possibly by Thomas Gosden; 59 pages, 26 cm.
    Includes Williamson's autograph manuscript copies of his letter to Samuel Tudor, May 16, 1816; two letters to Thomas Loxdale, August 9, 1814, and October 28, 1817; and letter to Samuel Bagster, May 28, 1809.
    Laid in: Index to "Barker's Delight"; manuscript, undated
  - 21. The Leisenring Color & Materials Book for Fly Tying, by James E. Leisenring, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Gift of Vernon S. Hidy, 1968.
    A pocket reference for fly fishermen designed by James E. Leisenring (1878-1951). Feathers, furs, herls & quills from the Leisenring Collection, assembled under the direction of V. S. Hidy.
    One of eight sets of colors and materials, with manuscript title page; 16 pages, 18 cm.
  - 22. Hunting and Fishing in Northern New York, by Frank French, 1884 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Gift of Lindley Eberstadt, 1969.
    Twenty-four photographs bound in brown leather, with a pencil sketch of Frederick H. Lum by Dr. French as a frontispiece; 21 cm.
    "No. 3 of 6 sets. F. H. Lum"
  - 23. Addenda, by John Hayford Thorold, 1821 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Autograph manuscript; 188 pages, 22 cm.
    Pages 138-152: "Fish taken at Syston, 1806-1827"
    Pages 53-137 and 154-188 are blank
  - 24. Angling journals, 1788-1796 (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
    Gift of Isabelle Tilford Wagstaff.
    Two manuscript journals recording kinds and quantities of catch, and companions present.
  - 25. Fishing, 1850 Oct 3 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Purchased from Henry Bristow on the Jonathan O. Bulkley Fund, 1994.
    Manuscript in an unidentified hand, with sketches of flies, ties, tackles, and fish, and a list of books related to fishing; 176 pages, 15.5 cm.
    With notes and sketches at the end, in an unidentified hand.
    Contains stamps of Low Moss Farm, Broughton-in-Furness; R. Tyson Johnstone; autograph of Jno. Dodson Skeleton, London, 1850; binder's ticket of J Sloper, stationer and bookbinder, London.
  - Manuel de la Pèche à la ligne, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    Purchased from Rodolphe Chamonal on the David Wagstaff Fund, 2003.
    French translation of Edward Fitzgibbon's volume A Handbook of Angling: teaching fly-fishing, trolling, bottom-fishing, and salmon-fishing; with the natural history of river fish, and the best modes of catching them. By Ephemera, third edition, with sketches.
    Bound manuscript signed B. Sautereau; 281 pages; 22 cm.
  - On fishing flies, by John Jackson of Tanfield Mill, May 1853, copied by James E. Leisenring, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
    Gift of Vernon S. Hidy, 1975.
    Bound autograph manuscript; 30 pages; 14 cm.
    From the James E. Leisenring Papers.
  - The Art of Tying the Wet Fly, by James E. Leisenring, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
    Autograph manuscript bound into two sections: "Tying Fishing Flies" (91 pages) and "The Mechanical End of Tying the Artificial Trout Fishing Fly" (76 pages); 21.5 cm.
    Published as The Art of Tying the Wet Fly, by James E. Leisenring, as told to V. S. Hidy (1941).
- Oversize
  - 8. The Nipigon River: account of a fishing trip in the summer of 1873 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - 14. Noted Angling Resorts, by Wakeman Holberton, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 27)